A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, 1798-1934, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence and Documents
  - Henry Clay, London, to John P. Todd, Paris 1815 March 30, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2933-a. (Box-folder 1:10)
    Clay scolds Todd for not writing and says he has not had "a line from any one at Paris since I left it." Clay is anxious to know how [James A.?] Bayard is and wishes to return to the United States. He has met Lord Castlereagh, but would be glad if Todd joined him in London. Clay expects a ship from New London to arrive in Portsmouth in sixteen days but does not know what news it will bring. He sees Lord Gambier tomorrow and hopes to visit Windsor.
  - Henry Clay, Birmingham, [England] to John P. Todd [1815] July 6, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Birmingham, 1815 July 7; mounted beneath engraving of Clay. #3121. (Box-folder 1:11)
    Clay writes that he left London on Tuesday [July 4, 1815] and arrived in Birmingham on July 6. Mr. [Albert] Gallatin was to leave London the same day but Clay presumes Gallatin "in my rear." He notes "we signed the treaty the day before I departed." Clay is eager to leave for the United States and tells Todd "Be you ready, for like Patrick Coutts, when dying, I wait for no man."
  - Henry Clay, Woodford, to [Martin D. Hardin] 1815 October 13, ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. #2908. (Box-folder 1:12)
    Clay writes to Hardin, Secretary of State of Kentucky, regarding his right to hold his seat in House of Representatives. "Having signed a Commercial convention with Great Britain on the 3d of July last, under a Commission from the President, it has become questionable whether my seat as a Representative, the right to which commenced on the 4th day of the preceding March, has not thereby become vacated." Clay regrets that he must call the Governor's [Isaac Shelby] attention to the matter and suggests that if an election must be called it should be soon, perhaps "a fortnight's notice might suffice."
  - Samuel Smith, Baltimore, to Henry Clay 1815 November 4, AL. Photocopy; original in Samuel Smith letterbook, p.26. #1729. (Box-folder 1:13)
    Smith writes that the sale of Clay's "yarns" left $5114.31 to his credit on his bond of $375. If Clay will send Smith "yarns of the quality of those sold by S. S. & B." [Samuel Smith and James A. Buchanan] Smith will either allow Clay twelve cents per pound against the balance due, or will sell them free of commission for Clay's account.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to William Thornton 1817 December 6, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1754-b. (Box-folder 1:14)
    Clay writes that he has purchased 2000 acres of land on the Wabash for two dollars per acre; he believes that "considering the progress of population and improvement" it will soon be worth fifteen or twenty dollars per acre. Clay understands that the Wabash, "which I think the fairest branch of the Ohio, has been exceedingly healthy this fall & summer." Clay mentions that Thornton's friend Martin Birbeck is settled not far from the Wabash. He concludes with a postscript: "I have a cordial dislike to appearing in the news papers & of course do not expect to be put there, in this instance."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to [John W. Hunt] 1818 January 22, ALS, 1 p. #9030. (Box-folder 1:15)
    Clay inquires about land values in Lexington, [Kentucky] and says that he must sell some property to meet financial obligations. Clay asks Hunt be his agent in the sale. He concludes by saying "[w]e have been 4 days, and will probably be twice as many more, in discussing Jackson's conduct of the Seminole War."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Charles Tait, Elbert, Georgia 1818 June 25, ALS, 3 pp.; docketed; silked; mounted beneath a blue "Blood's Penny Post" stamp bearing Clay's likeness. #3121. (Box-folder 1:16)
    Clay asks Tait to assist him "if it be practicable, to effect my reimbursement" of $325 advanced to Mrs. Rebecca Willisson. Mrs. Willisson "had a claim to some negroes in this state" and "brought a suit to recover them." Clay, "with more gallantry than prudence" agreed to stand security for the costs. He includes a copy of the receipt (made by John Spears, administrator for Jacob Spears) for the funds he advanced and says he "will be greatly obliged by any exertions you may make to get me the amount." Clay concludes by mentioning he has just heard of the capture of Pensacola. He presumes the action "is without authority; for if it has been, in pursuance of instructions, the Constitutional provision is a dead letter which confides to Congress the power of declaring War."
  - Samuel Smith, Baltimore, to Henry Clay 1818 June 25, AL. Photocopy; original in Samuel Smith letterbook, p.66. #1729. (Box-folder 1:17)
    Smith writes that he owes Col. [James] Morrison $1000 in taxes and has "taken the liberty to draw on you in his favor for that amount at 60 days sight."
  - Henry Clay, Lexington, to "Dr. Sir" [Samuel Elliot, Jr.?] 1818 August 1, ALS, 1 p.; docketed on verso; mounted. #3121. (Box-folder 1:18)
    Clay has transmitted to Mr. Dougherty a note for $4000 to be applied to his note at "your bank." He encloses a check for $1000 [not present] to cover reminder of the debt.
  - Henry Clay, Lexington, to Mr. [John F.] Watson 1818 August 8, ALS, 1 p. #1754-b. (Box-folder 1:19)
    "Being in Frankfort last week" Clay checked on the status of the suit of Edith Ross against David Barbour. He found that it was dismissed "several years ago for the want of security for costs." This was during Clay's absence. He believes that the suit can be renewed and suggests either George M. Bibb or Robert Wickliffe as "suitable counsel" since "I do not myself now practice the law."
  - Deposition of Henry Clay 1818 October 3, DS, 1 p.; witnessed and signed by Matthew Elder[?], Justice of the Peace, Fayette County. #3417-b. (Box-folder 1:20)
    The deposition concerns the sale of a slave by William Ellis to Elizabeth Gorney [?].
  - Samuel Smith, Baltimore, to Henry Clay 1819 July 9, AL. Photocopy; original in Samuel Smith letterbook, p.76. #1729. (Box-folder 1:21)
    Smith writes that he is in a "miserable situation" and is "under the necessity of drawing on you to pay Col. [James] Morrison" $500 for taxes. Smith states he has "no other means of payment" and begs Clay "to honour the bill." Smith's firm (Smith and Buchanan) failed following a run on the Baltimore branch of the Bank of the United States.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to [Benjamin] Watkins Leigh 1819 December 7, ALS, 2 pp.; silked. #1395. (Box-folder 1:22)
    Clay asks Leigh for advice on a legal question concerning the validity of the sale of John Clay's (his father) plantation, Euphraim, in Henrico County, Virginia. Clay mentions Richard Chapman, Henry Watkins and Richard Cocke.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to [Benjamin Watkins Leigh] 1819 December 18, ALS, 1 p.; silked; "M & K N York" watermark. #1395. (Box-folder 1:23)
    Clay received Leigh's letter and has written to Hanover "to obtain a copy of the act of renunciation" which his mother made regarding provisions in John Clay's will.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh 1819 December 26, ALS, 2 pp. #1395. (Box-folder 1:24)
    Clay has received a copy of his "mother's renunciation of the benefit of the provisions for her contained in my father's will" concerning the plantation Euphraim. Clay wishes to proceed with the action to recover the land and has asked Edmund W. Rootes to call on Leigh to "take under your direction the measures necessary for the successful prosecution." Clay then discusses the remaining heirs of John Clay and asks Leigh to advise if it is better to prosecute the case in the name of all three or two only. Clay prefers the case to be carried forward in Federal court.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh, Richmond, Va. 1820 January 5, ALS, 2 pp.; with detached address leaf; docketed. #1403. (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh, Richmond, Va. 1820 March 21, ALS, 1 p.; with detached address leaf; docketed. #1395. (Box-folder 1:26)
    Clay asks if it is necessary "to sue out letters of Administration, upon the Estate of my deceased brother, to maintain the Ejectment for Euphraim?" He repeats his question of January 20, 1820 concerning the possibility of obtaining administration without actually being present in Henrico County.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh, Richmond, Va. 1820 April 12, ALS, 1 p.; with detached address leaf; docketed. #1403. (Box-folder 1:27)
    Clay is informed by Col. [James] Morrison that he administered the estate of Clay's brother, George, in Richmond. Clay has requested Col. [Thomas] Tinsley of Hanover to work with Leigh in preparing the suit. He concludes by asking about the schedules of the court.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mr. [Benjamin Watkins] Leigh 1820 May 1, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. #1403. (Box-folder 1:28)
    Clay has sent Leigh's opinion to his brother Porter, who "is more interested than I am in the Ejectment." Clay concludes by asking Leigh to ask [Edmund W.] Rootes to record the deed from John [Clay] to Porter [Clay].
  - Henry Clay, Chillicothe, to M[aurice] Langhorne 1820 September 13, ALS, 1 p. #3920. (Box-folder 1:29)
    Clay received Langhorne's letter and "immediately addressed a letter to Col. [George?] Gibson" on Langhorne's behalf. Clay had hoped to see Langhorne on his journey back to Kentucky but "an unexpected summons from Mr. [Thomas] Wilson, Cashier of the Bank of the U.S." means Clay must now travel by way of Cincinnati. Clay concludes by stating that "subsequent reflection" has confirmed the opinion he previously gave Langhorne concerning the Bank of Limestone.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Mrs. M. Beckley, Lexington 1821 February 16, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #10012. (Box-folder 1:30)
    Clay writes that Capt. Fowler should retain the office of postmaster, but "he is greatly in arrears to Government" and "unless he makes some satisfactory arrangement very soon" he "will be deprived of it."
  - Henry Clay, Frankfort, to Thomas Dougherty 1821 December 7, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1109. (Box-folder 1:31)
    Clay encloses a check for $1300 [not present] to pay off the note coming due later in the month. Clay is "very anxious that the amount of Mr. Scott's note should be received and applied to the discharge of mine" and asks Dougherty "not to let him know that I have made an arrangement predicated on his default." Clay comments that the Kentucky legislature is still in session. The legislature is considering "sending me as one of two commissioners to treat with Virginia and to appear before that Ct. about the Occupying Claimant law." Clay concludes by mentioning that the "next Presidency" is being discussed in the papers and Dougherty "may confidently believe in an entire union of the West in favor of some Western candidate."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Langdon Cheves, Philadelphia 1822 January 23, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf; docketed. #2933-b. (Box-folder 1:32)
    Clay introduces Sam. Q. Richardson of Cincinnati to Cheves. Richardson wishes to "hold a conversation with you in respect to the revival of the Off. of Dt. & Dt."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Richard Morris, Richmond 1822 February 26, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington City, February 27. #38-79. (Box-folder 1:33)
    Clay writes to communicate the result of an enquiry he was requested to make at the Department of the Treasury by Dr. Morris. Clay was unable to go to the Treasury in person but sent a note to Mr. Pleasanton. Because of Mr. Pinckney's "regretted death" the business of the House of Representatives was suspended and Clay was able to visit the Treasury. He encloses a note for Dr. Morris [not present] and states that he will be happy "to serve him in this affair, if in my power." Clay notes that the Virginia House of Delegates has finally dispatched with "its part of the 'Kentucky Question.'" Clay is glad the House of Delegates "abstained from the expression of any opinion on our laws, as it did not feel itself justified in acceding to either of our propositions." Clay concludes with regards for Mrs. Cock [?] and Mrs. Kempe.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to B[enjamin] W[atkins] Leigh, Richmond 1822 March 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington City March 8. #1403. (Box-folder 1:34)
    Clay congratulates Leigh on being appointed a Commissioner to Kentucky and suggests he travel by stage from Richmond, through Washington, to Wheeling and then on to Frankfort. Clay concludes by stating that [Philip Norborne] Nicholas "is at my elbow, desires to be presented to you, and asks the favor of you to take care of him in the Ct. of Appeals until Wednesday, when he will be there." In postscript, Clay notes that Leigh will come through Lexington and asks him to "[c]ome to my house, sans ceremonies otherwise I may not know of your being in town."
  - Henry Clay, Philadelphia, to Thomas Dougherty 1822 April 3, ALS, 1 p. Negative Photostat; original at Pequot Library Association, Southport, Conn. #2933-e. (Box-folder 1:35)
    Clay has been detained for three days by "indisposition" which "has absolutely confined me to my room." He has written to General [Montfort?] Stokes, requesting Stokes to pay Dougherty $115. Clay asks Dougherty to send him details of the "arrangement you made with Commodore Rogers [sic] [John Rodgers] about the Carriage."
  - Henry Clay, Ohio River, to Genl. Peter B. Porter 1822 April 14, ALS, 4 pp. #5593. (Box-folder 1:36)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand at top of p. 1. Clay regrets that he did not see Porter on his return from Virginia in Washington City as Clay wished to consult "with you on a subject of great interest to me personally." Clay believes there is no viable candidate for the presidential election to follow James Monroe's second term from either New York or Pennsylvania. He notes that "in the South, there are springing up several candidates, my juniors in years and in terms of our respective service." Clay writes that his friends see nothing to "restrain them from bringing forward my name" as "[i]t is assumed that the Western States from Ohio to the Gulph [sic] of Mexico will be firmly and ardently united in my support." New York should ally with the western states in the election since "by lending its support, either to New England or to the South, it will not advance its pretensions one inch." Clay asks Porter if he "could not find time to employ your excellent pen in illustrating and enforcing those views of general and State policy which ought to determine the judgment of New York, and which we think obviously indicate the expediency of her looking Westwardly?"
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Richard Rush 1822 July 1, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #8991. (Box-folder 1:37)
    Clay asks for Rush's assistance concerning a bill passed in Congress regarding the Messrs. Streshlys[?].
  - Henry Clay, Cincinnati, to Jacob Burnet 1822 August 27, ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. #5363. (Box-folder 1:38)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand, following salutation. Clay had hoped to meet Burnet in Cincinnati, but Burnet's absence prevented him from doing so. Clay outlines the "dispute which exists between the States of Kentucky and Virginia" and explains that it will be resolved by "six commissioners, selected from States other than Virginia and Kentucky, which is to meet at the City of Washington on the last Monday of January next." Clay asks if "it would suit your convenience and inclination to attend, if the State of Kentucky should appoint you" as a commissioner?
  - Thomas Jefferson, Monticello, to Henry Clay 1822 August 28, ALS, 2 pp.; file draft, endorsed by T.J. Photocopy. Original in Thomas Jefferson Papers. Edgehill-Randolph Papers. #1397, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:39)
    Jefferson asks Clay to represent him in Kentucky in a lawsuit. The "misfortunes of the late Colo. Wilson Carey [sic] Nicholas" will have a negative effect on both Jefferson and his grandson, Thomas Jefferson Randolph as they are "bound to the bank of the US. in Richmd." for $20,000. Thomas Deye Owings of Kentucky was indebted to Nicholas for ten thousand pounds and Jefferson asks Clay "to have suit brought on it immediately in the Federal district court of Kentucky."
  - Henry Clay, Lexington, to Jacob Burnet 1822 October 5, ALS, 3 pp.; docketed. #5363. (Box-folder 1:40)
    Clay has received Burnet's letter of September 18 and states he is sorry that Burnet is "disinclined to serve as one of the Commissioners." Clay says that Burnet's concern about having formed an opinion on one of the matters to come before the commission should not prevent him from serving. Clay says that Burnet's opinions "are similar to those which have probably been made upon the minds of all the eminent Citizens of our Country. And if they are to be considered a valid objection, who shall we be able to prevail upon to serve?" Burnet's "want of acquaintance with the subjects of controversy" likewise should not prevent him from serving. Since the "Citizens of the States immediately concerned" are prohibited from serving on the commission, citizens of other states must make up the commission. Clay urges Burnet to reconsider and asks for his reply as soon as possible.
  - Henry Clay, Lexington, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh 1822 October 29, ALS, 2 pp.; silked. #1395. (Box-folder 1:41)
    Clay has not received any letters from Leigh since he returned to Richmond. Clay encloses a copy of his "report to the Legislature of the two agreements which we have entered into for our two States" [not present]. He comments on the recent Kentucky elections and mentions that "little has been said and nothing will be done" concerning the "attack" made against Judge [James] Clarke. Clay asks Leigh to tell [Thomas] "Ritchie that after having done so much, by the able and ingenious publications in his paper, against the Judiciary, to kindle the spirit which has existed in this quarter, it is a little unkind, on his part, to treat his deluded followers so roughly as he has recently done."
  - Henry Clay, Frankfort, to Benj.[amin] W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond 1822 November 18, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1395. (Box-folder 1:42)
    Clay writes that the Kentucky General Assembly has "unconditionally ratified the Conventions." He mentions that Jacob Burnet of Cincinnati and Hugh L. White of Tennessee will probably be appointed as commissioners. Mr. [John] Rowan will probably be appointed Clay's co-counsel. Mr. [George M.] Bibb "declines offering."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Benjamin W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond 1822 November 21, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1395. (Box-folder 1:43)
    Clay confirms that Jacob Burnet and Hugh L. White were appointed as commissioners. Clay and John Rowan were appointed as agents.
  - Fr.[ancis] Johnson, Washington City, to Benjamin W.[atkins] Leigh, Richmond 1822 December 10, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1403. (Box-folder 1:44)
    Johnson confirms the appointments of Jacob Burnet, Hugh L. White, Clay, and John Rowan.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh 1823 February 15, ALS, 2 pp.; silked. #1395. (Box-folder 1:45)
    Clay had "a conversation with the Chief Justice yesterday" and believes that the Supreme Court will not issue its ruling until "it has seen that the Legislature of Virginia will take no step towards an accommodation of the differences with Kentucky." Clay does not thing the "General Assembly of K.[entucky] would consent to strike out the clause of guarranty." He says that "both you and I ought to be now satisfied that popular assemblies are not happily organized for the consideration & just decision of those delicate & difficult matters which form the subject of treaties between State and State."
  - Henry Clay to Philip N. Nicholas, Richmond 1823 February 26, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #1921-a. (Box-folder 1:46)
    Clay encloses "the desired letter for Mr. Ambler" [not present] and states that he "felt at a loss to whom to write at Paris, but concluded that a letter to Mr. [Albert] Gallatin would be of most service."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Nicholas Biddle 1823 February 27, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed by Biddle; mounted; "JW Hatman Turkey Mill 1822" watermark. #3102. (Box-folder 1:47)
    Clay received Biddle's two letters dated February 24 and "immediately caused an enquiry to be made for Mr. [Jesse?] Hunt. Hunt "had taken his departure four or five days ago." If Clay had had the transcripts "a week ago his arrest might have been effected." Clay hopes "no difficulty" will occur with the arrangement made with [John J.] Marshall. Clay will remain in Washington another eight or ten days and plans to make a short visit to Philadelphia.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[enjamin] W.[atkins] Leigh 1823 October 20, ALS, 3 pp.; docketed by Leigh. #1403. (Box-folder 1:48)
    Clay encloses a deposition [not present] "to prove the facts you directed to be established in relation to my deceased brother Geo." Clay mentions Henry W. Watkins, Henry Perrin and Samuel Perrin of Virginia in connection with the lawsuit concerning Clay's father's estate. "A Mr. Chapman of Hanover and Col. N. Wilkinson of Henrico" were his father's executors. Clay asks if the death of Col. Morrison will have any effect on the "Ejectment." Clay is "greatly obliged" by Leigh's enquiries about his health; after seeing Dr. [John] Adams [of Richmond, Va.], Clay has improved and has "strong hopes" to regain his health completely. He mentions that he has received a copy of Ephraim May Cunningham's pamphlet Correspondence between the Hon. John Adams ... and the late Wm. Cunningham. Clay states that it "sheds no new light upon the character of the father or son." It seems likely to Clay that John Quincy Adams will be elected President as the "probabilities appear to me to be greatly in his favor." Clay notes that Genl. [Andrew] Jackson has been elected to the Senate. Clay understands "that the General has altered essentially his course of personal conduct; and has become extremely gentle, affable & conciliatory" and asks what Leigh would "think of receiving from him a sincere and cordial shake of the hand?"
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Nicholas Biddle 1823 December 6, ALS, 2 pp.; docketed by Biddle, date received Dec. 8, 1823. #3121. (Box-folder 1:49)
    Clay is indebted to "the Bank [of the United States] at the Lexington office" and has been "struggling to obtain the means to liquidate the whole debt." Clay was owed $10,000 by the Bank of Kentucky, which offered him "my choice of notes out of its bill box in Lexington." Clay selected notes and turned them over to Mr. [James] Harper "to be offered to your Board at Lexington as collateral security only." Harper informed Clay "that the measure adopted by the Bank of K. has produced considerable excitement with the makers of the notes." Clay asks Biddle to "lay the matter before your Board in the hope that it will make the requisite order to receive the notes." Clay includes a list of the notes he wishes to assign to the Bank of the United States [not present].
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Robert R. Henry, Albany, New York 1824 January 14, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. Endorsed by Henry. #3472. (Box-folder 1:50)